As science advanced during the 18th and
19th centuries, the industrial
revolution changed the way people worked
and organized their lives. It also
changed the way they looked at the
world.
[music]
>> [music]
>> A new generation. of philosophers soon
began to challenge Kant's theories.
Whilst they accepted the idealism, they
were dissatisfied with the limits he put
on understanding and reason and so
sought to transform his idealism.
[music]
What is rational is actual and what is
actual is rational.
Gayorg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel was born
in Stuttgart in 1770 and studied at the
University of Tubingan.
Much of his writing is complicated and
is difficult both to understand and to
expound.
He published his encyclopedia [music]
of the philosophical sciences in 1817
and further expanded editions followed
in 1827 and 1830.
The encyclopedia [music]
is a hugely ambitious work. Its aim is
to take in the whole of reality, history
and knowledge in a systematic form. Um
well encyclopedia published in 1830 the
third edition comes in three parts in
the end three books. First called the
logic and then a philosophy of nature
and a philosophy of mind or spirit.
And the idea all along I think is to
develop a system of way of thinking that
will resolve problems in the natural
world in the way science treats the
world and in the human world politically
and ethically and so on by using the
categories that he set out in the logic.
There is much in the encyclopedia that
is influenced by Aristotle.
Hegel was both a rationalist and a
romantic.
He had a keen sense of how the past
affects the present. He claimed to have
produced a complete map of all possible
knowledge and reality. Hegel saw
medieval Christianity as a prime example
of what he called the unhappy
consciousness.
Judaism emphasized the separation
between man and God. Christianity sought
to unite man and God through the
incarnation.
Yet there is still a gap between the
changing nature of the world and the
unchanging nature of God.
>> He wants to integrate philos uh religion
within philosophy. Um and the way he he
does it um is to argue that basically
the insights of religion are the same as
the insights of philosophy but just
expressed or understood in religious
terms. Uh so he just characterized it as
picture thinking uh thinking in terms of
images or representations.
So religion will talk about God and
we'll talk about the incarnation, we'll
talk about creation and so on. uh and he
thinks they're all legitimate ways of
thinking about the world in a pictorial
or story form and philosophy will is
able to um recast those ideas in more
philosophical forms. Um so for example,
you know, religion talks about the
incarnation or religion talks about
creation as God creating the world.
Well, what does that mean
philosophically? Well, it means that
there's a sort of rational structure
inherent in things. And when we talk
about God creating the world, we just
mean, well, you know, in sort of
Einstein phrase, God doesn't play dice.
So what does that mean? Well, we just
mean that the world has a rational
order. It's no accident in some sense
that things broadly speaking are as they
are. We can understand why things have
to be a certain way. And that relates to
the religious idea of God and God's
creation and so on. So Hegel hoped that
he could satisfy give a place for
religion in that way within a
philosophical framework.
>> Hegel goes on to deal with reason and
what he calls spirit while contrasting
the ancient world with the modern world.
>> What he means by spirit is is a
particular way in which um consciousness
the conscious of a people or a community
or period is then at home in the world.
So he talks for example about the Greeks
as uh as everpresent spirit. Uh and the
reason he talks about the Greeks there
is that he he has a picture of the
Greeks as having this integrated view of
the world at home in the world um such
that they didn't seem to suffer from the
various problems and tensions of the
modern world. So spirit, what he calls
spirit was realized in some sense with
the Greeks was apparent in the Greeks
because they had this kind of
>> [snorts]
>> um unity with the world. Hegel's view is
that for for a variety of reasons that
at homeness that spirit and that period
was lost. Um
and that's really because he he he tends
to treat the Greeks as a kind of
childhood of human consciousness. So
much like a child has a certain kind of
happy relationship to the world again
supposedly uh before all the anxieties
of adolescence set in. So the Greeks had
a sort of simple straightforward but
rather naive view of the world. They saw
it as rational. They saw themselves as
integrated within their communities and
so on. Uh we don't have that anymore.
Ours is a more anxious time. We have all
these tensions. we we
not so convinced that the world is a
hospitable and and place at which we can
be at home. Um but then he hoped that
spirit as it were would return. This
again this kind of integrated picture
would return um when when these problems
of modern consciousness could be
resolved.
>> In philosophy of right Hegel deals with
social ethics and the state.
His claim that the rational is the
actual has led critics to claim that he
wrote the book as an apology for the
authoritarian Prussian state under which
he lived and that as a result he should
be seen as an influence on Nazism.
It's not clear again it's not obvious
that Heaggel was a was a a reactionary
figure
but in historical terms um but I think
also we could you can think of the
question philosophically I mean again
Hegel as usual is trying to strike a
balance so um
he he does want um as I say the
individual to feel integrated within the
state it's not that he wants to get rid
of any notions of individuality. Um but
obviously that means that um it can seem
as if he he nonetheless because he wants
to integrate the individual he he wants
to still place some limits on the ways
in which the individual can criticize
the state or step outside the state. Um
now even here uh it's not clear that
Hegel's saying the individual should
always obey the state or should always
feel at home with the state should
always accept the decisions the state
should make because again he draws a
contrast between the rational state the
state where there are proper mechanisms
for dealing with individual interests
and and balancing them off against each
other um and the nonrational state. So
he does talk about figures in history
such as Socrates and Christ and so on
who were in sense rebelling against the
state of their time and he sees that as
perfectly legitimate because they're not
living within the rational state. So
it's only it's only if the political
conditions are right as it were that
Hegel thinks the individual should by
and large go along with the decisions
the states are making.
No philosopher since Hegel has laid
claim to the same kind of
comprehensiveness and universality of
thought.
Up until um maybe 20 20 years ago or so,
Hegel was a very marginal figure. People
tended to read um uh study up to Kant
and then they would sort of leap from K
to Frager or something of that sort.
Hegel would be just this sort of dark
period where where it all became obscure
and difficult and um bizarre and and
nobody thought it should be taken
particularly seriously. Um and it's more
like as if somebody you know read Plato
without reading Aristotle. If you if you
read Kant and then don't bother to read
Hegel you're you're missing out on a
whole range of important developments.
And not just Hegel other postcantian
idealists like Shelling and Fika as
well. you're missing out on a whole
range of developments that can appear
very obscure and difficult and and uh
peculiar when you first look at them,
but actually tap into rather deep and
interesting issues that we're only now,
I think, within the analytic tradition
beginning to rediscover.
>> [music]
>> The main characteristic of Shopenhau's
writing is its elegance and clarity. In
1819, he published his main work, the
world as will and representation.
Six years earlier, he had produced his
doctoral dissertation, the four-fold
root of the principle of sufficient
reason.
He believed this should be read as an
introduction to his main work.
He claimed his philosophy was the
unfolding of a single thought and
acknowledged a great debt to Kant.
Schopenhau set out four forms of the
principle of sufficient reason.
One of Schopenhau's important
contributions to philosophy was his work
on the world as will. The world as we
experience it according to Schopenhau
has the character of will.
This does not mean will in the way
perhaps understood today but the raw
energy of the universe. Shopenhau means
will in terms of stars exploding,
cooling, [music]
galaxies expanding and contracting.
This phenomenon has no consciousness or
personality.
In the third part of the world as will
and representation, Schopenhau considers
art and what he construs as platonic
ideas.
Schopenhau dismissed the ideas of God
and the soul.
For this reason, he has been accused of
being the most pessimistic among German
philosophers.
But this is perhaps unfair. Schopenhauer
pinpoints music, sculpture, poetry and
the arts generally as the portal into
the world that would otherwise be beyond
our reach. This is because whilst
enveloping ourselves in art, especially
music, we escape the shackles of time
[music] and space, even our physical
selves.
[music]
Born in Prussia in 1844, Nze studied
classical philology at Bon and Leipig
universities. At the age of 24, he was
awarded a professorship at the
University of Bal, something very
unusual for the time. His life was
however plagued by illness and in 1889
Nze suffered a mental breakdown and
spent the last 11 years of his life
being cared for by his sister.
One of Nze's main assertions was that
traditional Judeo-Christian values had
lost their meaning for many people. They
were formed long ago by societies much
different to our own. He recognized that
religion was playing a far less
important role than it used to. He was
convinced that traditional values
represented a slave morality. That is a
morality created by weak people who
encourage kindness and similar traits
because such behavior serve their
interests.
Once we break down our existing
morality, nature claims we can pursue
our own destiny untrabled and realize
our true potential.
Nature often refers to this unleashing
of possibilities as daring to be
imaginative, innovative, courageous and
so on.
This unleashing of one's potential was
coined by nature as the will to power.
And as there is no afterlife, no god, no
reason to restrain our capacities or
talents and that we are masters of our
own destinies, nature claimed we should
live our lives for their own sakes, as
if lives are works of art as it were.
For this reason, he has a kind of
aesthetic understanding of life,
although his vision of life is far from
picturesque.
the life affirming
and in a sense the notion of health is
really important to him.
But health is not stasis. It's not a
kind of stable state. It's a kind of
warding off of disease. And because for
nature even the self isn't a unity as a
kind of there's a kind of potential
difference within what we think of as
the unified self.
Um
the self is only a unity in so far as
all the different forces within within
you might and energies within you might
tend temporarily in the same direction.
So the will to power is the will is not
power over another. It's a will to
um a kind of an urgic will where all the
energies are directed towards the same
end. Um and he says things like whatever
doesn't kill me makes me stronger. Um
and uh the willed to power is used to
explain
um uh digestion
uh uh eating
um reproduction and uh the will to find
truths. Now he's not offering the will
to tr to power as a truth. Um the will
to power is yet another interpretation
of the world. It's that it's a more
lifeaff affirming one. During his
lifetime, Nze produced an influential
body of work. Both Mussolini and Hitler
read Nze extensively.
The Nazis extracted quotes from [music]
Ncher's work to use in their propaganda.
And for some years after their demise,
their link with the philosophers's work
overshadowed his impressive contribution
to philosophy. Nze was not a Nazi but
his work reverberated throughout the
artistic and cultural world inspiring
playwrights, poets and composers. when
nature um went mad towards the end of
his life um nature's sister Elizabeth
Fer
who was married to one of the most
celebrated anti-semmites in Germany
um took um nature uh and sort of made a
sort of fetish of him almost you know he
was there and people would come and
visit him and she also took his
unpublished notebooks the so-called will
to power um and edited them and his
other works as well in a way that made
him look like uh an anti-semite.
And it was possible to do this because
nature writes metaphorically.
He's also not writing for the common
man. He's writing for the man who's out
of his time um who knows his work, who
will not um read him literally. So there
is a certain responsibility in terms of
the way that nature wrote. Um he knew
that he could be read anti-semitically.
He said he made it him sick. Uh he said
it made him laugh. He said it was a
gross distortion of his work. But at the
same time he still wrote in a way where
where it was possible to read him like
that. But really it's to do with his
sister primarily. I think that his his
work was given such an extraordinary
weight by the Nazis and uh the Nazis
weighted Vagnner and nature almost
together.
Marx was born in Tria in 1818 and
initially studied law. He soon turned
his attention to philosophy and for a
time edited a newspaper in Cologne.
It was when he moved to Paris that he
met Friedrich Engles and in 1848 they
wrote the Communist Manifesto.
The proletarians have nothing to lose
but their chains. They have a world to
win. Working men of all countries unite.
In his youth, Markx had belonged to a
radical political group called the Young
Hegelians, but later became disenchanted
with Hegel's philosophy. In a sense,
Markx doesn't disagree with Hegel's
project that that you know uh the the
aim is to create a society of a kind of
harmonious society where people are
integrated and feel part of a community
and so on. Um but Heg but Marx thinks
that Hegel is rather naive and and
optimistic in how he Hegel thinks that's
going to be brought about. Um so for
example Hegel thinks that the bureauc
treats the bureaucracy um as a you what
what Hegel calls a universal class. So
the bureaucracy is meant to have this um
rather uh worthy uh concern with the
well-being of the community as a whole.
uh and that's the role of the
bureaucracy within the community that
they're sort of there to um take make
sure that everyone's interests are
treated equally and and fairly and so
on. Um and Marx is just contentious
about this and just sees the bureaucracy
as a rather corrupt institution
um
which is in the service of the the
monarch or whatever and certainly isn't
this this um rather benign um idealized
um part of the community that Hegel
thought of.
>> Today Marxism is unfashionable.
Capitalism has conquered the globe. Yet
his contribution to political philosophy
can't be ignored.
>> One one influence I think is in terms of
his theory of justice as we might call
it now. Um because again it's a
contentious issue within Markx whether
he had a theory of justice whether Markx
was just just a social scientist just
trying to understand why societies
change and develop and where they're
going to perhaps where they're going to
go. but he wasn't interested in making
judgments about whether one society is
better than another or more just than
another. And and they, you know, you can
certainly find passages where he's
critical of those notions. Um they're
not they shouldn't be of concern to, you
know, good communist thinkers. You
shouldn't be going around judging
societies in that way.
>> [music]
>> Only the truth that edifies is the truth
for you.
Sir Kakagard is generally seen as the
founder of existentialism.
In 1840, he was about to marry but broke
off his engagement feeling it was
incompatible with his calling as a
philosopher.
He was an intensely religious man and
felt the Danish church had distorted
Christ's message.
>> One of the things that the church does
is disguise
uh to people the um paradoxicality. They
make Christianity s the church makes
Christianity sound too easy
um too comfortable
um too ethical.
So for example in fear and trembling um
he is writing about Abraham as the
father of faith
and he takes the story from Genesis
where God commands Abraham to take Isaac
his son up Mount Mariah
and kill him. Um, and Abraham doesn't
know that at the last moment God will
provide a lamb or a ram um as uh a
sacrifice instead of his son.
And he says that we might go to church
and hear a preacher talking about how we
should honor Abraham as the father of
faith etc. without focusing on the fact
that this was a would-be murderer. If a
preacher um told the story of Abraham in
the church, then um KGA indicates that
um the preacher would also be horrified
if any member of the congregation went
home and on the basis of a message from
God actually went out and murdered his
son.
>> The dominant theme of Kiekagard's work
is man's relationship with God and here
he disagreed sharply with Hegel.
Um for khigar there is no synthesis.
There are different modes and ways of
life. Um and we have to choose between
the different modes. [snorts]
And it's not that religion or faith
involves a synthesis of other previous
stages. It's a different mode um and is
irreconcilably
different.
Um Hegel also thinks of the state in
terms of um Christianity. So he's in
favor of sort of state forms of
Christianity. He thinks of Christianity
is tied to reason. Um and he thinks of
this gradual progression of the spirit.
And Hegel is is um different from Khagar
in respect to all these things.
In either or, Kagard argues that we have
a choice between two ways of living, the
aesthetic and the ethical.
>> Khagar
uh is concerned
with so to speak seducing the reader. Um
so presenting the reader with choices in
such a way that the reader has to choose
what sort of self to become, whether to
become an aesthetic and ethical or
religious type self. And it's almost as
if there are um parallel possibilities,
parallel universes almost. um and that
at any moment in time there are these
different possible paths or routes that
one might follow and through choice turn
oneself into a different kind of self.
Um but it's not that we know in advance
what sort of self we are so that the the
the choices are are made free freely.
But on the other hand, Khagar is
developing a notion of a self in which
the self only ever exists in relation to
another. Um, and so it's not a
completely autonomous self. It's a self
that's guided.
Um, and because the reader has to make
their own choice, so to speak, Khagar's
very concerned with indirect
communication, not giving or the answer
himself, but leading the reader to the
point at which they can see what the
choices are.
>> Kagard's Christianity is a very
Protestant one. His key notion is that
of angst or dread resulting from a life
given over to the senses.
Kieekard believed in subjective
thinking. The source for truth is
personal. A person's choices and
decisions are between him and God.
It was this emphasis on individual
choice that was to influence future
philosophers.
[music]
There is no worse lie than a truth
misunderstood by those who hear it.
Pragmatism was a reaction amongst
American philosophers against idealism.
The leading lights of the movement were
William James and CS Pur.
Pragmatism was a philosophical movement
that emerged in the United States
predominantly around Harvard uh in the
1860s, 1870s and the years following. I
think it originated in a metaphysical
club as Per called it that he and James
belonged to in Harvard um in the early
1870s. It contained them, some other
philosophers and significantly I think
some lawyers.
It was Pers who emphasized the practical
bearing we conceive the object of our
conception to have. This idea which Pers
called pragmatism was taken over by
James. For Pur pragmatism was a kind of
tool for clarifying the contents of our
ideas and hypotheses and things we're
interested in. And I suppose one thing
he hoped that he'd get from it was a
demonstration that lots of ideas and
hypotheses were actually empty. they
didn't need to be dealt with and in
particular a lot of the traditional
questions of philosophy could be
dismissed by showing to be meaningless.
James however applied the idea to truth
itself.
James believed consciousness to be like
a river and invented the term stream of
thought. In his principles of
psychology, he puts forward five
principles concerning consciousness.
The first of these was that our thoughts
tend to cluster into personal
consciousnesses which roughly means that
you know if there's a thought it's my
thought or it's your thought and lots of
thoughts are connected just through
being in the same mind through being
mine or through being yours. His second
claim was that within any consciousness
thought is always changing. There's a
kind of continual process of one thought
following another giving away to
another. And I guess you don't find
periods of sort of stasis where nothing
much is going on.
The third claim was that thought is
continuous. So I suppose that means that
there's not just one thought followed by
another thought followed by another
thought. There's a kind of continuous
process whereby thoughts evolve and
develop.
The fourth claim again pretty plausible
is that most of our thoughts present
themselves as about external things. You
know, so that James might have been
thinking about Harvard University or
about his friend Charles Pur. And so if
we're going to understand how thoughts
work, we have to understand how they can
be about these independently existing
things.
But finally, James emphasized that in
our thought when we're thinking about
things, we're always attending to or
focusing on particular features of them.
So I'm not just thinking about Harvard
University. It might be thinking of
Memorial Hall or thinking about uh the
green in the center of the university or
something of that kind. So we need to
understand how thought can be selective
in the way in which it attends to
things. Meanwhile in France, Ori Bergson
was a great influence on William James.
He is perhaps best known for coining the
phrase the vital spirit.
>> Bergson was a philosopher who took
evolution very seriously. I think he'd
probably been influenced by Darwin's
writings, but he rejected the sort of
mechanistic basis for evolution that
Darwin offered. Indeed, he he wanted to
think that evolution did involve some
kind of progress that through time
things were getting better. Whereas the
Darwinian story doesn't allow for that
possibility at all.
So he claimed that evolution was in a
way driven by a sort of creative urge or
a a vital spirit which was a kind of
explanatory principle I suppose that
would have no place in mechanistic
physical accounts of how the world
works. I think he thought that the same
process was actually present to us in
our consciousness, in the way in which
we make decisions because we were aware
of the ways in which our choices are
influenced by memories, influenced by
the past, but we're also aware, he
thought, that they're not determined by
the memories, that we are actually free
to choose and indeed free to make things
better. So either way, this reference to
progress gives us a rather optimistic
view of things, optimism about what we
can do and also optimism about the way
things are going. But it's interesting
that it carries with it
um a commitment to a sort of vital
spirit, an explanatory principle that uh
has no place in the physical sciences or
anything of that sort. So it carries
with it the thought that in explaining
living things in biology and in
psychology and so on, we have to appeal
to well a doctrine that's often called
vitalism. The thought that there is this
vital spirit there as an additional
explanatory mechanism
in creative evolution. Bergson says the
whole universe must be seen in
historical terms.
Every stage is a development of what has
gone before.
The present contains nothing more than
the past. And what is found in the
effect was already in the cause.
[music]
Ludvig Vitkinstein was born in Vienna in
1889 but became a naturalized British
citizen.
He initially trained as an engineer but
from 1912 to 1913 he studied
mathematical logic under Russell.
Like Russell Vickinstein was interested
in language and its uses.
The limits of my language mean the
limits of my world. What Vickenstein's
interested in is ordinary language, the
kind of language that we use all the
time. Uh not some ideal equivalent that
philosophers may be able to set up.
>> In later life, Vitkinstein became
disillusioned with some of the theories
he had propounded in the Tracticus. You
get the impression when you're reading
the tractatus that it's as if he thinks
that the only basic linguistic move
that's of any concern is the move of
saying what things are like
saying what is the case to go back to
the very first sentence of the
tractatus.
And of course that is something that we
often do. We give each other
information. We pass on information to
to each other in all sorts of ways. And
we can be right or wrong as the case may
be. If you ask me for instructions to
get to uh somewhere, I can give you
directions and that those directions may
be correct or incorrect as as the case
may be. But he later began to realize
that um that's by no means all that we
do with language. There are all sorts of
other things that we do as well as just
convey information.
We we greet one another. We thank one
another. We praise each other and blame
each other for various things. A whole
variety of different linguistic moves
that we make that hadn't really been
recognized in in the earlier work or so
he later thought.
Vitkinstein's views began to change in
later life. It is only since his death
in 1951 that much of this has come to
light.
Many of his texts and lectures were
published postumously.
These included the blue and brown books,
typescript copies of lectures he gave at
Cambridge. Their influence was
significant.
In philosophical investigations,
Vitkinstein deals with language and
numbers. He begins with what he calls
language games.
When Vickenstein in his later work talks
about language games, really this is um
a metaphor for helping us to understand
the variety of different things that we
can do with language other than just
talk about what is the case or convey
information to each other.
So um when people greet each other in
the street and say hi or hello or how
are you, they're for Vickingstein,
they're playing a kind of language game.
They're making moves in a game which
don't consist in conveying information.
When you say hi, you're not conveying
information to another person. You're
greeting them. And um the other example
that I mentioned earlier was was
thanking. Somebody gives you something
and you you express your thanks. Again,
that's not a way of conveying
information. That's a particular kind of
move that we sometimes make in a in a
very important language game that we
sometimes play. The point is simply to
remind us of the huge variety of
different things that we can do with
language.
>> He also deals with rules for the
development of series such as that of
numbers.
>> Vickingstein was very uh interested in
the whole question of rules and
following rules in his later philosophy.
Although I think perhaps people have
sometimes exaggerated his interest
because they've thought that what he was
claiming was that language is always
governed by precise rules which um
actually it seems to me is in direct
violation of the point that we were just
making. It's not always governed in very
precise ways by precise rules. And there
are plenty of linguistic games that
develop in a a rather
um unregulated way. For a large class of
cases, though not for all, in which we
employ the word meaning, it can be
defined thus. The meaning of a word is
its use in language.
Perhaps the most controversial section
of the book is that dealing with the
naming of sensations. It [music] has
been seen as a revolt against the
Carteesian framework.
>> On the Carteesian view, it's as if
there's a little private theater that we
each carry around with us and that we're
observing what's going on on on that
private stage.
And Vickinstein says, well, um, the
reason that we think like that is that
we're once again forgetting the huge
variety of different ways in which
language can function.
So that to take one very simple example,
think about the claim um I'm in pain.
Suppose that you're asking me whether um
a part of my body hurts or not. And I
say yes, I am feeling some pain at the
moment or yes, it does hurt or whatever.
We're inclined to think, as Vickingstein
himself perhaps would have thought when
he wrote the trackctus, that what this
is is um a commentary on what the world
is like, that it's a way of conveying
information. In the same way that I
might tell you that there's a chair over
there, um I'm now telling you that
there's a pain in my leg. And um the
question then arises, okay, what's the
nature of this information that I'm
conveying? What what um what am I
commenting on? what am I reporting on?
And once you raise that question, it's
then not very long before you're going
to be starting to think about this in
cartesian terms. Think, well, the pain
is something that only I have access to.
So when I'm telling you that I'm in
pain, obviously that's something that I
can know in a way that you can't. It
must be because I'm talking about this
little private world that I carry around
with me. And Vickistein says, "Well, no,
we we're forgetting that language does
function in a huge variety of ways."
And although I'm in pain is a little bit
like there's a chair over there, in
other ways it's very unlike that. And we
could just as well think of it on the
model of simply saying ouch, which is
another way, another linguistic way in
which people react to pain. a much more
simple, much more primitive linguistic
reaction to pain.
But nevertheless, that's um part of the
language that children have to learn.
And that's one of the ways in which when
children are in pain, they do react to
their pain. So Vickenstein says, well,
if we think of it more like that, we'll
um begin to resist some of those
cartesian temptations. will begin to
wonder about whether it even makes sense
to say that I can know that I'm in pain
in a way that you can't.
Vitkinstein believed it was necessary
that language should be public, not
private.
This insistence on the public context is
the most important point in
Vitkinstein's theories. He did not
believe though that theories should
necessarily be stable in propositions.
Other philosophers have backed
Vitkinstein's opposition to Daycart.
uh even those philosophers may actually
be making the same kind of mistake as
Daycart, the same fundamental mistake as
Daycart if Vickenstein is right because
they too may be saying that um
the the the sentence I am in pain
reports a particular fat actor is is a
claim about what is the case and needs
to be understood in those terms. And
then what they're trying to do is to
understand it in those terms and trying
to determine what kind of thing pain is.
And because for one reason or another
they're dissatisfied with the
traditional carteesian picture, they
come up with their own alternative
account of what kind of thing pain is.
But if Vickenstein's right, those
questions may be inappropriate in the
first place. Uh if we do think of the
sentence I am in pain more in terms of
[snorts] the exclamation ouch. We're
going to be much much less interested in
raising those questions in the first
place if indeed we think they're
legitimate questions at all. We're not
going to be asking what kind of thing
must pain be like in order for us to
make the claims about pain that we do.
We're going to be focusing much more on
how the language of pain actually works
when you
um say things like it hurts and I'm in
pain and what the conditions are for um
counting as as correctly using that
little bit of language.
So that um modernday physicalists
may be as guilty of a basic carteesian
error as Daycart himself was.
Hell is other people.
Jean Porad was a successful playwright
and novelist as well as a philosopher.
The influence of Haidiger can be seen in
his first book being [music] and
nothingness published in 1943.
Such believed that because we are
conscious beings, we can make ourselves
of our own free choice. The existence of
free choice is a key element in Sat's
philosophy.
In part four of being and nothingness, S
writes of the dangers of allowing one's
freedom to be usurped by a supposedly
stable world of things.
The world of someone who does this is
unstable and false. He says things at
that stage that sound very like
determinism. He says that every act has
a cause. And the the the real difficulty
is to understand how he can say that and
still be you know somebody who's who's
supporting a kind of rad radical freedom
for human beings.
The point about um claiming that every
act has a cause is that he conceives of
causes very very differently from the
determinist.
For him this notion of nothingness once
again plays a very important role. Um if
for example um I go to the shop to buy
some milk or something like that, the
determinist is going to explain that
action by by saying that there are
certain pre-existing objective facts and
subjective motives. Namely, um the
objective fact was that there was no
milk in my fridge and the subjective
fact is I want some milk. Right? And
these two somehow interact and produce
the action. sort says no on the contrary
what causes my action is something that
doesn't exist namely it's what he calls
an absence
and so consequently what causes you to
go to the shop in this case is not the
simple fact that the milk there isn't
milk in the fridge but that the milk is
absent. it's entirely different.
And
immediately he's already got um a
conception of the cause of actions which
is entirely at odds with determinism
because determinism wants to say that
actions are caused by pre-existing
states of the world and states of the
person. Here we've got something being
caused by something that doesn't exist,
namely an absence. One area of Satra's
philosophy they have acknowledged as
brilliant is his concept of bad faith.
Bad faith is how Satch describes an
individual's denial of their own
freedom.
modern versions of that attitude of bad
faith although this is a slightly
controversial thing to say is is might
be thought to be the the kind of
increasing medicalization of all kinds
of things where people are inclined to
say that um that I don't know everything
from dyslexia to dyspraxia as we now
call clumsiness
to um uh I don't know um the SAD
syndrome, seasonal effective depression
to um things like um
we're now told that that caring too much
for others is a kind of illness.
Um where uh over and over again, every
time you open the newspaper, you
discover there's some new medical
category. And really the point of the
medical category is precisely to excuse
the person from responsibility for his
actions. Now I don't want to make any
blanket claims about such medical
categories. [snorts] Um but in many
cases I think that it really is the
point that and that sort would look at
them and say um you're actually in bad
faith. Um you know you are actually
responsible for your behavior. Um you
know just stop making excuses for
yourself.
Later in life, S turned to Marxism. He
felt that existentialism could show the
relevance of Marxist concepts by
interiorizing them.
And what of the future?
Perhaps we should end where we began
with the words of Aristotle.
For it is owing to their wonder that men
both now begin and first began to
philosophize.
>> [music]